hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights I'm your host
Daris PV Wayne and today I'm talking
with Marilyn sendera Marilyn is a lectur
a lecturer in philosophy at the
University of wangong Australia her
research focuses mainly on the
phenomenological tradition particularly
its intersections with cognitive science
and she has a particular interest in the
role of time and how it shapes our
cognition and experience in 20 5 she
wrote the paper being in the world
temporality and autop poesis which
explored the inextricable intertwining
of age in the world the Confluence of
hiigaran perspectives and in activism
and
self-organization and to my eyes at
least a focus on these domains makes her
work amable at least in principle to the
insights of active inference and among
other things it is the viability of that
project that sort of coming together
that we will be investigating today
Marilyn thank you so much for joining me
and welcome to the show thank you so
much for having me darus I'm really
pleased to be here yeah yeah it's an
absolute pleasure I mean um I sort of
came across You by finding that 2015
paper and I love it um I went back and
read it again uh sort of in preparation
for for our podcast today and it's it's
so insightful um and yeah I I just as a
starting point for anyone listening I
highly recommend they go check that out
um but let's dive into some of the
things you spoke about in that paper
there's a quote that you took uh that
you referenced from verela um Francisco
verela who who sort of introduced the
term aut paresis with Matana into the
biological literature in 1980 and he
wrote a universe comes into being when a
space is severed in two I wondered if
you could help us unpick uh what he
meant by
that yeah so that's uh that's um so frle
thank you so much for for your your kind
words but Myer I think everybody loves
loves hearing that so um yeah so verela
in general has been a huge uh influence
on on how I look at cognition I think
since I wrote that paper I've kind of
come to um more newon say yes
understanding of of what outer PES and
autonomy and activism are about but yeah
this this this idea of um of the
cognitive process as being fundamentally
a relation
and precarious and uh something that
can't be understood by looking at at any
of the one components involved in that
process in isolation right it's that
fundamental idea of of in a sense
cognition is is always this precarious
process in ttention um it's the creation
of a boundary it's the creation of a
separation a barrier but also always at
the same time uh a barrier that has to
be porous and a barrier that that uh is
always something that is under threat
that has to be maintained um and there's
there's always that question which is
something that's fascinated me of uh the
the the kind of the tension between just
how much that barrier has to be
maintained versus how much it has to be
open to change which is I think also one
of the the really interesting points of
of
conversation with with inference but
yeah this this idea of of of cognition
World and Action there is there is a
boundary there's a separ ation there is
this this sense of um what in subsequent
kind of inactive literature is called uh
both self- production and self-d
distinction especially right so that
something brings itself into being
something maintains itself something
distinguishes itself and thereby we get
this kind of whole complicated wonderful
condition of having world right
fantastic gay it's interesting that you
mentioned that there's a kind of
philosophical question there about the
point to which uh you know where does
where does that self- distinction uh
start and end um yeah I mean I think a
lot of the active influence literature
is converging on a a point of vagueness
sort of a soriz paradox perspective that
you know when does a grain of sand
become a pile or a heap and and so on um
I guess another philosophical question
is does it you just to start with a
really fundamentals here about like this
coupling does it even make sense to
think of anything as having a kind of
autonomous uh essence or nature without
some coupling
environment that's a brilliant question
and so ultimately in a sense I think
what a lot of the the literature that my
work moves and wants to do is move away
from this idea of having an Essence
right so there's there's already that
kind of Prior question of can you have
an entity can you have a system can you
have an organism that that is clearly
kind of itself and is clearly kind of
distinctive without having you know
anything as as kind of substantive as as
an Essence um and what does it mean can
there be a kind of I guess
non-teleological concept of of what it
means to be alive that so some folks
look at it or you know yeah just is is
there a way of talking about Essence
without talking about Essence um in a
sense um and so yeah so so overall to me
I think and I think all of the
discourses that
my work moves in and and what strikes me
about active inference as well is this
idea that yeah coupling is is
fundamental there is no such thing as a
non-relational at least not a
non-relational living system a
non-relational cognitive system
cognition life is
always a matter of structural coupling
um and yeah that's that in a sense is
kind of what we have to start from sure
yeah I think in I think that's a good
point that uh we're definitely skeptical
of substant
substantive Essences sub substantive say
it right that time uh selves in the
sense that active inference
casts uh thingness as a statistical
distribution um and sort of uh builds
off dynamical systems theory about this
kind of idea of attractor sets or sort
of the peak of probability distributions
I actually just reading Manuel delanda's
book that came out last year the
phenomenology of the materialist
phenomenology and he without even
referencing active inference talks also
about these kinds of basins these
attractor basins and I guess if we did
want to just take a broad rush I guess
we could start defining things as being
in some ways the statistical manifold or
or or this attractor base and that's
cool that's yeah that's a nice
perspective um so let's let's sort of
Jump Then to autop poesis um maybe it'll
be useful for you to just give our
audience a kind of overview view of what
that term means um sort of coming from
the verela literature and then we can
kind of fold in active
inference yeah awesome that sounds great
it's it's funny that you mentioned that
book I literally just bought that last
week it's flying around te it's good
it's good I'm enjoying it yeah awesome
that's that's good to hear I look
forward to reading it yes so I'm so I I
should flag firstly that you know this
this is like my um attempt to explain
what these concepts mean so of course on
the one hand there are very kind of
clear definitions especially in a very
landmar onest initial proposal of of
these terms but since then the whole
kind of you know so-called Ultra poetic
and active approach a term that in
itself is is contested because lots of
people point out it's not just about
aesis anymore um all of these terms are
are you know super contested and um
their whole literature is about you know
kind of defining them in relation to
each other and so yeah so I umum I kind
of I I follow a bunch of of contemporary
folks in and cashing out um outter pois
as as a kind of a a type of
organization um wherein an organism
essentially uh both produces and
reproduces itself and distinguishes
itself um and so uh one of those
contemporary folks is is Ezekiel deer
who conveniently has those those self-
production self-d distinction and he
points out you know you you can't have
an out system without having both of
those so you can have a system and that
kind of manages to Define and
distinguish itself but if it doesn't
reproduce the kind of processes that um
that Define it then it's it's not
autopoetic and you can have a system
that is able to kind of reproduce its
components and processes but if it's not
able to maintain kind of a precarious
boundary um then it's it's not
autopoetic either and and so that this
is the idea that this is this is kind of
an an Oran organizational principle um
so in in verand matan's original account
this was meant to be a definition of
life as such essentially um and since
then it's become a lot more complicated
so of course ver and Matana themselves
developed this um much more extensively
and these days I guess the more
appropriate term to kind of use this
autonomy right so there's this kind of
general idea of a self-producing self
identity that can be kind of
instantiated in lots of different ways a
lots of different um structures and uh
there's there have kind of been lots of
other tools added to the to that
conceptual repertoire so one of the
reasons uh so one of the the kind of the
main Innovations for example has been
the addition of this this concept of uh
of of adaptivity right so where outro
pois is no longer seen as as kind of
being sufficient for capturing what
cognition is all about there's also this
this idea that every living system every
cognitive system
has essentially produces these kind of
Standards on all do these things how do
these these kind of fundamental features
both scale down and scale up and so that
idea of of aiming to do well rather than
aiming to do worse so there is there is
the IDE here and I do think it's it's
plausible that this is something that
happens you know at the most basic level
of of life and cognition that's kind of
the where the switch flips uh in a sense
to to a living cognitive system um and
and you notice so for you know for for
this kind of branch of an activism life
and cognition are essentially
intertwined so've got a living system
you've got a cognitive system and so I
think um I think just the the capacity
to respond to uh to to stimulate and and
circumstances and what's happening in
the environment the capacity to kind of
have a meaningful
perspective um in kind of not a very you
know thick psychological sense but just
in kind of basic respond to the Seline
that way rather than that way I think it
is you know it is it is absolutely
plausible that that's kind of a
fundamental aspect of what it means to
be alive and so then the interesting
question kind of is how do you get from
that how do you get from you know a
bacteria moving away from areas where
there's I don't know less nutritional
concentration or where it's bad stuff
moving towards the good stuff how do you
get from to kind of our complex
reflective metacognitive psychological
processes and yeah I think that's that's
kind of where a lot of these discourses
can kind of come together to flesh out
that developmental scale that scale of
cognitive complexity how does this basic
responsiveness this basic kind of world
involving World producing not wanting to
die aspect of life how does that then
scale up to the very kind of complex
reflection that we're able to do and
it's yeah it's really interesting I
think to consider how active inference
can kind of potentially contribute to
that maybe quantify some stuff add some
tools to the
repertoire yeah I think again I can't
speak for everyone in the field uh
because I'm like everyone else I guess
kind of a newcomer um well at least for
a lot of people but I think what's
really fundamental to the complexity of
cognition under an act of inference
framework is the depth of temporal
planning so again as I said in my
introduction you're really interested in
time and I think what what we're finding
is that like a complex organism like us
what might make us definitively complex
as our capacity to do counterfactual
reasoning so take your example of a
bacterium um it it can't it doesn't have
a model of the world where it can sort
of at least not in any significant way
use um retrospective inference to inform
future inference so it doesn't know for
example okay there's neutri over here
but actually I might suffer that long a
short-term loss for the long-term gain
of being in this region right so it
exploitation uh exploration distinction
is like it's just less nuanced I guess
um they're humans how does that sort of
sound to your ears that maybe what we're
looking at here is a uh depth of
temporal
planning yeah that that sounds great so
um generally speaking so um I I love the
idea and this is something that I kind
of try to pursue um of cashing out the
spectrum of of cognitive complexity in
terms of temporal complexity right so
largely you know including along the
lines that that you've just mentioned
and so there's there is some you know
really interesting literature already on
this that kind of points out um some of
the the ways in which um yeah those
those basic structures of kind of future
directedness and and anticipation and
planning can become more complex
especially through as you said right
through our relationship to essentially
more complicated kind of future right so
counterfactuals unpredictability
uncertainty uh there's there's some cool
new work looking at you know spikes of
entropy um that sort of thing and that
to me is also one of the the places
where really the phenomenological
tradition becomes super relevant and and
super interesting right because there's
there's this kind of consistent IDE IDE
that um as and this this this starts
before in a sense so not quite before
but a little bit outside of
phenomenology in the work of Al bur and
this idea that uh so for him cognitive
complexity and complexity of embodiment
is explicitly linked to kind of more
radical confrontations with uncertainty
which also comes with those
confrontations being more meaningful
right so the more complicated you get
the difference between us failing and a
bacter and failing there are all these
existential meanings risk failure uh
carries so much so much more
significance in in the scaling up of
those mechanisms and then you get that
in the phenomenological tradition too
this this idea that um yeah we we have
more and more complicated Futures but
also you know kind of more complicated
relationships between our own histories
and the future and um and yeah I I like
the idea of of as you said you know
cashing that out terms of of more
complicated different richer forms of
things like anticipation yeah there's so
much there um I mean yeah I've been
saying stuff that you know people are
even grounding Consciousness or or you
know trying to resolve the hard problem
through this route so the the you know
maybe the function of Consciousness
let's not get to the kind of deep qual I
don't think we need to go there is to
kind of you it's it's fundamentally
episodic to use what's happened in the
past to inform what's happening uh you
know you know what's going to happen in
the future or what might happen in the
future um yeah that's that's really
beautiful and that has a as you say kind
of scale up to significance I mean it
made me think of Ern Becka and the
denial of death um and this idea that
like that finality I mean again and Hyer
that that finality is kind of
fundamentally framing of our being in
the world um as you can tell I you know
I like to use this podcast also to point
people in directions um of where they
could read to uh or or listen to to
learn more about these things I think a
really wonderful paper um outlining some
of these themes is by Andrew cor Coran
javanni Petula and yob Hoy um from our
static agents to counterfactual
cognizers that's a 2020 paper and it's
really wonderful um so anyone who's
listening who's interested in maybe like
how are we going to carve out these
distinctions between simple organisms or
non-active organisms simple simple
living organisms complex living
organisms they do a really good job
giving a kind of framework in which to
to assess those those ideas um it's
another sort of interesting
philosophical question that's really
rearing its head at the moment for some
reason there's this distinction between
realism and
instrumentalism um I was wondering you
know that it's a Live question in active
inference for example whether the the
mark of blanket which acts as the
boundary between internal States and
external States whether that's a
instrumental tool for us as scientists
or whe that actually had some kind of
true ontological status I was wondering
if you'd had any thoughts about whether
autop poesis so
self-organization uh self production and
self
distinction is a uh just actually an
instrumental an instrumentalist thing so
it's just a way of us to describe what
seems to be happening um at different
levels of biology but it can even go
broader than that or whether it's
actually an imperative it's actually you
know a genuine thing it's a mechanism
that's occurring at it within these
organisms yeah that's a that's a really
really interesting question darus thanks
for that and yeah I um I did see when I
was I was trying to do a little bit of
homework um for for this and then trying
to read up on an active inference a bit
I I saw there there was one paper that
kind of made a throwaway remark of you
know whatever the metaphysical stages of
the mark of blanket might be and I
thought right what's that about so that
I think that that kind of explains
explains what that was but yeah I mean
it's it's in a sense that's kind of a a
fundamental metaphilosophical and
methodological question in again kind of
all of these discourses right it's it's
it's something that affects all of these
different models of cognition something
that you find in the phenomenological
tradition too like are these these
structures are they heuristics are they
kind of you know the best possible thing
that we can come up with to to make
sense of what's going on or are they
actually out there what does it mean for
anything to actually be out there in
this sense and on on the one hand I I
don't want to you know get away from the
kind of the the materiality of of
cognition which is you know kind of
crucial to all this like you can you can
see this this stuff happening um you
know in different kind of cognizers and
I guess it becomes these are structures
that become more and more heuristic and
instrumental as you kind of move up in
in cognitive complexity and you know
when it comes to especially kind of
structures like outer PES and autonomy I
mean you know get applications of this
sort of thing to the behaviors of groups
for example and you know you you get
this kind of scaled up in things like
systems theory and I guess there it
becomes more and more um instrumental
but one one thing that kind of comes to
mind uh as you're raising that point is
this kind of this there's really
interesting insistence in the corner of
an active discourse that interests me
the most in in the embodied mind that
there
is we don't have to and this is kind of
deeply phenomenological as well we don't
have to worry that much about these
questions because there is this this
kind of we do have an insight
into what is really out there so to
speak and and into the processes of life
and the processes of cognition because
we're living cogniz as ourselves there's
this idea which kind of actually Echo I
think you know hiig his famous idea that
like we're particularly well positioned
to do ontology because you know where
these being
who have insight into and who care about
the structure of being itself and within
yeah in in you know the embodied mind
there's this idea that as living
cognizers being alive and being
cognizers the same thing gives us an
insight into the structures of life and
cognition so kind of any heuristics that
we use even if they do end up being
purely instrumental heuristics kind of
give us something genuinely important
and insightful about what's happening
out there because in a sense for us
there is no such thing as you know just
a neutral out there sure there kind of
interesting idea of like a privileged
Insight um into cognition by virtue of
of being cognizer so I guess yeah as in
terms of the phenomenological tradition
too it's less of a question that I'm
particularly concerned with it's
interesting but yeah there's there's
there's more of a sense of you know
let's look at what this stuff is like
from the inside without being too
concerned about what what kind of
actually is out there so to speak fair
enough um I guess like the the harder
scientists might you know their ears
might prick up when they hear that
actually our stance the fact that we
take a stance on the world uh
yields a greater possibility for insight
because they might say well every
insight you're going to have is going to
be colored in a way by your own personal
experience your history your cultural
baggage I mean very postmodern take as
well so do you also in a sense do
phenomenologists have to
recognize the bias or yes the coloring
of these
insights and to what extent therefore is
objectivity of the cards for a
phenomenologist yeah that's a that's
another great question and yeah
absolutely so in a sense the idea that
you are that any insight that you come
up with any any knowledge any claims are
always going to be
situated um they're always going to be
richly shaped and informed by not just
your personal history but of course you
know broader history social
norms um your you know kind of cultural
expectations um the situatedness of if
knowledge is kind of a fundamental
starting point for phenomenology and so
it's less about taking objectivity of
the table and more about redefining what
objectivity is and so I think that's
that's one of the the kind of key points
of resonance for example between
phenomenology and and an activism right
so it's is this idea that again
knowledge is always fundamentally
situated it's always historical it's
always uh socially culturally emo uh
embodied and embedded um and so that
means we have to think
about um what it is that that we're
actually aiming for or and and you know
there there's there's no problem in
getting rid of this this or in not being
able to achieve this kind of sense of of
neutrality that isn't really possible
for a sense making organism anyway right
because we enact our world um and we we
bring forth our worlds in ways that mean
we're not going to encounter uh the
world in in kind of neutral you know
gray pure brute matter terms um and yeah
that's that's I mean that's you know a
widespread point across a whole bunch of
discourses the interesting question then
is how do we
reconfigure what we actually mean by
objectivity and especially of course how
do we build into subjectivity into that
um and yeah so I think you know that's
that's the idea that knowledge is is
fundamentally situated is is is very
much it's not a problem for
phenomenologists of course there is you
know there's this this kind of history
of well phenomenologies trying
to discover these you know General
structures that make cognition possible
um so isn't there you know some kind of
tension in saying all knowledge is
situated but also here are the universal
structures that make all situate
knowledge possible so that's kind of
that's a that's an ongoing kind of
interesting tension and problem but yeah
um I think it's it's more about
redefining what kind of what we mean and
want by objectivity well it's a you know
it's a uh self Dee defeating element of
kind of any nonobjective or or theory
that postulates non-objectivity right I
mean like if the postmodern claim that
truth is relative is relative then that
claim itself is relative so anyway we
it's a it's a kind of Wormhole that we
don't necessarily need to go into I I
mean that it would be also interesting
to have a mathematician on here um
because I could imagine they would have
some some gripes with our inability to
get hold of the object you know the
objective but again there's no need to
go to go there um I did have a question
though um I mean again there might be
one of those that are isn't too relevant
to the discourses that you're engaging
in but it's a question sort of about
ends um and and purposes so you write in
um one of your papers I'm not sure it's
the 2015 one it might be another one
that an autopoetic system is autonomous
in that it is its own product it does
not exist in order to bring about
something else to accomplish some
externally defined end but rather to be
and perpetuate itself its identity is
its task you also say in the same paper
the organism's purposive aiming towards
the overall end of
survival as well as its more immediate
needs in successfully navigating
environmental circumstances are
structured by a directedness towards
something which has not been reached yet
I guess at first glance there might be a
superficial tension there um can it be
dissolved just by saying that what we're
talking about in with
perpetuation um in the first quote is
survival in the second quote is that to
do with the kind of identity conflation
is that the way out of that potentially
tricky
tension yeah yeah so that's uh that's
more just kind of a a problem of um the
that particular expression so the the
point about um an an organism's kind of
identity being its own task rather than
anything else it's not to say that you
know a cognizer literally does doesn't
have anything else to do except VI um
it's it's more about this idea that in
order to count as an as you know an
autonomous living system
um it has to have endogenous ends right
and so it's survival has to it's it's
kind of its its drive to to you know
persist to maintain itself to resist the
possibility of annihilation has to come
from within itself it's not something
that you know it's kind of one of the
classic ways of distinguishing say an an
an artificial from an a living system or
a living from a non- living system right
it's it's not a living system is not
something that has been given its Ends
by somebody outside itself like say a
designer or a programmer uh and where
its end is you know to do something
whether it's it's you know a line of
code that's meant to do something or
whether it's I don't know a sort of
basic machine intended to do something
the point of the living organism is
itself is is its maintenance of itself
and then of course in pursuit of that
self-maintenance that resistance against
you know the constant threat of
annihilation it pursues all sorts of of
other projects which you know you can
kind of think of if almost is and I
think this is why heiger is especially
helpful it's kind of arranged around you
know this this kind of
fundamental self-c concern and you know
as as organisms get more complex you get
more and more sort of complicated
project arranged around uh what hiiga
conveniently calls you know the for the
sake of myself um thanks H and yeah yeah
no gotta gotta love the Hants but um
yeah yeah and you know and there is
there's those projects kind of take on
more
existential uh significations as well
and what it actually means to be
self-concerned is no longer just I want
to not starve but you know I have a
particular conception of what I want the
story of my life to look like sure yeah
this is a really interesting Avenue
because it it sort of rears its head in
active influence literature as well
active influence conversations because I
think it's still a Live question I might
be wrong but I see it still as a Live
question is to what degree is all the
organisms
do to what degree is that just a
minimization of free energy and I guess
the problem at least in active inference
is that basically everything can be cast
is B optimal so this is called the
complete class theorem so even if I do
something which seems antithetical to my
survival under some priors it it's Bas
optimal and so I guess we either could
cast this as not being a form of self
organization or we could just expand the
notion of self I guess in a deflationary
way to mean everything that a thing does
and it's just based optimal under that
scheme so again it might be a kind of um
empty question
but just to say it's it's live at least
um within Act of inference as well I
mean you know you thought about this on
the inactivist or autopoetic end it was
a question I had which is you know I
think you you you said both in your
paper and here that aesis is certainly
necessary in the same way that
minimizing free energy is necessary in
some quite trivial sense for the
Persistence of an organism but it might
not be sufficient to Define exactly what
that organism is again that's the open
question
um if it's not sufficient just it might
be a very silly question what else do
organisms or cognizers
do yeah absolutely see so generally
speaking um autois and autonomy aren't
you know they they are seen as necessary
but not sufficient conditions and so
that's where uh the concept of
adaptivity which I touched on earlier
comes in right so kind of one of the the
kind of key discourses uh has for the
past probably couple of decades or so
maybe a bit less actually maybe closer
to like 15 years suggested that yeah
that the necessary and sufficient
conditions for cognition and life are
autonomy and adaptivity right so that
that idea of being able to respond to
whether you're doing better or worse and
and steering away from from doing worse
so that the idea is that that might be a
kind of you know basic enough condition
that can still be instantiated by lots
of very very simple organisms but that
can scale up in all sorts of interesting
ways including um you know some of the
the cards that we talked about but there
is you know there there is still kind of
this this live debate and this um this
this ongoing question of yeah is is that
enough in terms of sufficient conditions
for life and cognition but also
generally you know um how do you draw
the line between uh is that enough to
draw the line between a living and and a
non-living system and I know that um so
like I said I I you know I tried to do a
little bit of of reading especially on
on some of the dialogues between folks
working in active inference and folks
working in an activism before this and I
saw you know that's kind of been one of
the questions where folks have kind of
asked each other you know maybe maybe
this is this is something where these
perspectives can collaborate it seems
like you know across all of these
discourses there's the concern it looks
at these theoretical Frameworks can
apply to all sorts of different systems
how do we for example go from this to
explaining what it means for an organism
a living organism to have a meaningful
perspective do we have enough resources
to be able to flesh out what that is and
how it becomes so much more
complicated um and yeah so I think I
think that kind of that continues to to
remain a live issue in lots of really
interesting ways sure and also quite a
at times heat debate uh between and
researchers which I will not get into uh
I want C out to that um let's let's go
to haiger then uh because he's a sort of
uh specialty I guess of yours or or
focus a topic of focus um you know
scanning through just the active
inference
literature researchers might not know
too much about haiger there have been
papers on hle Merlo Ponte obviously is
very important because of the embodied
aspect of his work um I inip poito on
last week and she spoke about Simone DEA
and how her existentialism can be
married to act of inference but hiiga
for some reason seems to be uh the
elephant in the r room who never really
gets mentioned I think a good place to
start and you're going to be far better
place to do this than me is to tell us
why Hyder go is just so radical uh and
my thinking about this is just framing
him as kind of the anti- day cart so
sort of setting up that philosophical
history that might be a complete broad
brush uh
misidentification but where the kind of
cartisian tradition
was uh and how that kind of got
collapsed by haiger and others might be
a good place to
start yeah absolutely and and so so one
thing I I I'd want to say at the start
too is that so even within an active
discourse there hasn't been that much um
looking at at hiig go broadly speaking
so it's always you know as you said
Merlo Pony hor it's great to hear that
um Min is is doing some work on some Ro
run because yeah I um I've done some
work on her myself and from what I know
of her I I think I'd agree with um with
that perspective so yes yeah it's it's
interesting that there is this this kind
of significant Gap and so in terms of
what makes hiiga radical and and
interesting and
useful um in kind of opposing that
cartisian tradition so uh to me the
first thing that kind of stands out and
this is something that I touch on in
that that older paper that you know that
um that you came across being in the
world um temporality out poesis is that
the way he talks about the relationship
between cognizer and world so I'm using
the word
cognizer I don't read heiger in a
particularly Orthodox way I don't
particularly care about reading haiger
in an orthodox way either um and so yeah
so the the way that he talks about the
cognizer world relation
is both startlingly similar to and also
particularly useful for uh all of these
kinds of discourses that look at
cognition as active
situated um action oriented being about
you know meaning generation being of
relational right because in in haig's
account of being in the world you
essentially have the same problem that
we're we're still talking about in these
discourses which is on the one hand
emphasizing the kind of the
relationality the the extent to which
cognizer and world are intertwin such
that you can't understand either part
from the other why while on the other
hand not kind of completely dissolving
the cognizer into the world right so
unlike you know some models of say for
uh of you know embodied cognition there
is still this sense of holding on to a
core of
self-concern um and this is this is why
I argue it's especially resonant with
the inactive tradition holding on to
this this idea of those boundaries right
we've again we've got that central
question of uh a living system is one
that defines itself it has to be a
poorest boundary but it nonetheless has
to be a boundary so again for hiding of
the subjects not dissolved into the
world it's fundamentally it produces the
world it enacts the world it's
integrated with the world and yet it
still has that kind of core of of
self-concern and and of of what you know
an activist call adaptivity this kind of
future directed self-concerned planning
and so
um yeah as as phenomenologist are often
accused of kind of being unfair to De
card and and I do think in in many ways
we are but you know as of thinking as of
the cartisian tradition more
specifically than de there is yeah that
that kind of radical insistence on
undermining dualism insistence on
undermining separation of mind and World
subject and object but also mind and
brain brain and World subject and and
body right this idea that these are all
kind of fundamentally constitutively uh
connected um and so I know this has
already been a long answer one other
thing I I wanted to throw into and this
is something that I think is especially
underappreciated in all of these
literatures is how hiig then links all
of that to time right so all of the
phenomenologists um and this is
something I I try to argue too like time
is fundamental to phenomenology every
phenomenologist has an account of time
uh and you know and they're all cool and
great and interesting um hiig accounts
stands out in particular because it is
fundamentally linked to practice it's
fundamentally linked to kind of salient
responsiveness to self-maintenance to
motivation to this kind of very basic
practical normativity and to what we've
been talking about that you know that
kind of temporal complexity that that
you know that sense of of like life
itself is fundamentally kind of
anticipatory and that then gets
complicated in all sorts of rich and
cool ways and so so yeah so you've got
this model of of time that's kind of
fundamentally linked to practice
normativity motivation self-c concern
adaptivity so yeah my my contention
there is like hey look if if you know if
we're looking at time and and time is
super important to all these embodied
cognition discourses why not look at
this model of time that kind of comes
prepackaged with this idea of of
relational cognition and practice sure
yeah yeah I mean the parallels there or
at least the the way that Ina activism
and active inference are clear well even
if it's implicit clearly informed by
hiigaran perspectives is is kind of very
transparent they're very obvious um yes
I think the disdain that later
phenomenologists have for dayart might
be influenced by the disdain that the
earlier phenomenal had just had for
dayar I think there's a good I was
researching up I just think there's a
good story about um Hider throwing sra's
book in the bin because SRA sort of
reinvoke Cartesian self
you know probably quite an angry chap as
well
um Tiger's personal life um perhaps
there is there is the not egg there yeah
there's a lot that I mean actually the
on complete side note there's um the the
history of philosophical arguments
between like you know supposedly quite
like stoic uh Placid men because it's
all men is is a is a fascinating I read
a really good book ear this year about
um the this fight that Vicken Stein and
K POA had at cambridge's philosophy
Society um which I recommend highly it's
called Vicken Stein's poker anyway it's
a complete side uh side note um I think
it might be quite useful for people to
because they might not know what you
mean by practice uh and this notion of
practice and Tool and and how this all
links into being and being in the world
perhaps an example would be useful
because I think I've been thinking about
this because I I just wrote a paper with
some really wonderful co-authors as well
so credit to them um about Flo and my
thinking about Flo States is that it's
it again this is a Live question but it
might be rooted in the same mechanisms
um that draus called skillful coping and
hiding word of called a-h handedness
right so maybe rock climbing is kind of
part of the same category as opening a
door or gripping a water bottle right um
so I think you know this might again
this is another Live question is the
degree to which uh people conceive
themselves as cartisian egos there might
be an intuition at least when we're
talking intellectually to say well I am
this rified self that has this kind of
Separation in time and space and
identity from the things on which I act
perhaps you can give us an example
just from everyday life where hiiga
reveals to us that that Intuition or
that uh perspective might not actually
correspond to the uh the
phenomenology yeah that's a that's a
great point and um just on the the the
wienstein book I think I came across the
same one it also talks about fantastic
case where I think he he threw chalk or
keys or something at one of his students
head and it actually yeah I think he was
like seemly quite abusive um yeah but
also yeah obviously extremely accute and
intelligent I'm not going to demean VI
canstein I again these also not here to
defend themselves so who am I to who am
I exactly there is there is there is a
point to this right so there is kind of
I think you can always see this this
like this this continuing of in a sense
a cartisian tradition of thinking about
what it is that philosophers do and the
kind of activities that are important
where it's there this idea that you can
divide what's you know what's happening
in here the really important stuff from
you know kind of acting in the world and
then practicing in the world um and that
you know yeah these these so-called
Geniuses they get away with terrible
behaviors like that because we we
privilege we prioritize what's going on
in KS as opposed to to kind of how they
actually act in in the world and so yeah
so coming back to um your point then
about um about practice or just in ter
terms of what I mean when I talk about
practice it's just a kind of the very
basic means ends kind of connection that
you have Through Time right and so
controversially and and I don't think
other hog garant would agree here it's
you know even like uh bacterium swimming
away and and swimming towards you know a
better nutrient gradient is is kind of
like a primordial instantiation of
practice and also get you know more
complicated as you said with with how
equipment and Tool being so just to to
kind of to give a quick overview of
those Concepts and then maybe try and
come up with an example um so uh for
hiig together it's it's something that
will be familiar to to folks who work in
you know embodied cognition or
potentially even active inference it's
this kind of overturning of the
traditional hierarchy of how we do
things where the idea is that you
encounter the world in Practical terms
first before you then kind of encounter
them in you know more Quantified
theoretical terms so that you know
you're not and and I yeah I think even
within active inference this holds like
you're you're not you know the
Terminator walking around with kind of
you know numbers scrolling across your
vision figuring out you know that object
classified as a table made out of cedar
wood is you know three met small so on
and so forth you you encounter it first
in terms of well I've got heavy stuff I
want to put stuff down um or you know I
don't want to bump into the sharp edge
of that table and you're not even you
know explicitly thinking about this
necessarily in such terms it's more
about encountering the world in terms of
calls to action uh what folks in
ecological psychological affordances you
know different possibilities for for
doing things um and there is I think a
risk of of kind of under under inter
Eliz this process right so fer there is
still very much this sense that what you
encounter isn't isn't like you know this
this kind of just pure mass of complete
non-conscious absorption you're still
kind of encountering things as things
and there is still very much the
possibility of at least transforming
some of those practical relationships
into for example linguistic
relationships if you need to um but yes
so in terms of examples I mean you know
heiger gives us the classic example of
the hammer yeah um but something that I
actually like using uh in class when I
talk about this uh is so I I I game a
lot too much um and I feel like this is
something that fundamentally kind of
made hiding as account of practice more
feasible to me right because you know
say you're you're playing with keyboard
and mouse or you're playing with a
controller um you are very much so
immersed in the game world world that
you're not really consciously reflecting
on uh these these tools that you're
using you're not you know you don't have
this kind of
consistent uh metacognitive reflection
on yourself as being separate to the
mouse separate to the control you're
just you are just acting right um and
it's it's when they as you know Hada
famously says with the H it's when they
break down that yeah they become
apparent as objects so that the kind of
the terminologists like do sorry they're
like using so-called breakdown cases
because the idea is that we're so
immersed in kind of everyday practical
existence that it's hard to philosophize
it's hard to gain that distance and so
we sometimes need for to wait for things
to go wrong in order for as haiger says
the structures of the world to
illuminate to light up to become
apparent and
so when the Mouse runs out of battery at
the worst possible B the controller
drifts or lags and all of a sudden you
know it's it's not just that you become
aware of yourself as holding this object
you kind of all of these different
structures of the world light up you
remember that this is a game you become
more aware of the hit boxes uh the game
physics all of the different little
mechanics all of the numbers that the
game constantly generating and it's like
the whole world lights up and at the
same time you have this kind of this
tragic moment of distance and the
interesting thing is that that breakdown
is both an interruption but it's also
super useful if you happen to be in a
philosophical mood when the house the
controller breaks down because then you
can go aha now I'm aware of of all of
these structures right no that's that's
really convergent with yeah my my
perspectives on this um yes I think the
hammer example so he good gives this
example of a hammer or hammering at
Nails I also don't think it's the best
example like the most canonical example
of a handedness or or or definitely not
flow I mean I guess Hyder is lacking
examples because he didn't have probably
didn't have rock climbers or Surfers or
Gamers but I I'm hard pressed to imagine
a hammerer so immersed in hammering I
mean to be honest um I think it would
involve a lot of yeah metacognitive
processes what what we call epistemic
foraging so a lot of exploratory
Behavior even if that's mind wondering
so I I I take your point I think the
game example is a lot better and yes
you're absolutely right it's not just
that this uh rified sense of self
emerges as you say the world itself
shifts or or is modulated by that
breakdown so I talk about how um the you
know I give an example in my paper about
a violin string breaking during a
concerto and the violin had been in
float you know the violin no longer
seems to be presenting affordances so
the violin itself seems to be changed
and suddenly you get all of this sort of
concomitant selft talk as well and you
get all the Dows and you're suddenly
very aware of the audience and the
reason at least the reason why we uh
postulate that that might be the case is
because your free energy minimizing
system has kind of entered into a
epistemic mode it needs to resolve
uncertainty about the world it doesn't
have the availability of just like very
high expected utility or or or pragmatic
affordances so yes we can split this
notion of affordances shout out of JJ
Gibson into epistemic and pragmatic
affordances and that's a really nice
distinction with an active inference a
question uh that popped into my head um
actually the question before um I was I
spoke to John BVI um a couple of weeks
ago and that was published and it was a
wonderful conversation and John was um
really really insightful and I said
something like well I think there's a uh
intuition of over you know which guides
us to see ourselves as some kind of
cartisian
ego and
John and yes I think it's very much
contextual bound but I think underlying
that at least I think it's a you could
propose that there is this intuition
John said well I actually think that
might be more of a cultural phenomenon
um and actually it's a very Western idea
and it's sort of built off the way that
we structure society and the way that we
see ourselves do you think that uh
there's a kind of I won't use the word
innate but instinctual or intuitive
sense in which we model ourselves as a
kind of rified ego or do you think as
John says it's very much bound up in
context whether that be cultural or the
kind of practice that we're under taking
at that
moment yeah I think that's a fantastic
question
so I don't know I I find myself kind of
leaning in both directions right because
on the one hand I do think there are
significant cultural social historical
factors that are going to shape this you
know there's there's of course the you
know that the kind of famous distinction
of of um I guess Western if if you want
to use that word
individualism um as opposed to you know
uh kind of other views of thinking about
the self in relation to
community um and uh I was I was reading
a wonderful paper about Ubuntu
Philosophy for example um which kind of
you know says it's it's not it's not the
cartisian thing of you know um I think
therefore I am it's it's we are
therefore I am right so that kind of
fundamental community and relationality
and so yes I I absolutely do think that
there are um kind of specific factors
influencing this on the other hand um so
one of the interesting things that kind
of I guess the phenomenological
tradition which is also super
eurocentric right um brings up is this
idea that the way that cognition Works
kind of almost perversely encourage
encourages us to forget how cognition
works right that it's it's this this
kind of process these processes cover
their own
tracks and make us kind of you know
Overlook just how practically immersed
we are um and yeah there's this this
kind of interesting idea of you know
again for example in in hiiga there's
this idea that because we are
fundamentally practical creatures that
means we're likely to kind of lose
ourselves in the Practical everyday to
an extent that we start kind of you know
forgetting the existential ramifications
of what's happening and we we kind of
start losing in a sense that kind of
explicitly futural aspect of ourselves
or you know and and and we forget our
mortality our finitude and all of that
and you get this kind of throughout the
phenomenological tradition that the very
the very things the very um kind of
purposiveness the embodiment the I guess
the depth of our investment as well just
how meaningful the world is to us
meaning that kind of the
precariousness of our condition and and
all of these kind of the cogs underneath
uh are things that we like to try and
ignore and that we tend to turn away
from and and that is also something that
you know you again you do find in lots
of philosophical traditions around the
world this idea that we do kind of have
this this maybe not inate but we
certainly have a very common tendency to
lose sight of ourselves forget ourselves
in the very kinds of practices that you
know are fundamental to the kinds of
creatures that we are so there's always
this kind of danger of losing sight of
ourselves there's always this kind of
danger of seeing ourselves in an
atomized uh isolated uh individualistic
way I was actually um just just earlier
this year in in and ethics 101 we were
going through um various uh forms of
confusion ISM and there is this This
brilliant um idea in in kind of uh one
of the the the schools of confusion ISM
that once you kind of start mistakenly
thinking of yourself as an isolated
object rather than as being part of the
fabric of everything and being involved
in in everything being relational then
it be it it's almost this Snowball
Effect where you actually become more
and more self-isolating you feel
lonelier because you're thinking of
yourself right isolated that makes you
more selfish and it has all of these
kind of flowing and effects yeah so I
guess yeah on the one hand I absolutely
think there are immensely important
historical social cultural specificities
on the other hand I find it really
interesting that lots of philosophical
traditions talk about our tendency to
kind of misconceive of ourselves
these individual so that might be quite
widespread yes that's that's that's
really useful um yes I mean I guess it's
it comes to a philosophical question
about what selfhood is uh and how much
we're being swayed by our own well it's
only a of misconception or Illusion if
you buy the notion in the first place
that the self is a kind of atomistic
rarified thing so again it's it's um
it's kind of up for grabs but I think
what's lovely about AC inference and
again I'm going to toot its horn is that
it kind of gives a computational account
of this so I think what the way it would
be answered now and I you know this is
actually an area of work that I really
want to keep delving into personally is
that this hiigaran notion
that we tend to forget exactly how
cognition is when we're immersed in the
world I think that makes sense because
what what we're doing when we do have a
ray of f sense of self is accessing all
the parts of our cognitive Machinery
that rely on us on a memory on
proposition right because we're in this
epistemic mode we're resolving
uncertainty we're testing out model
parameters right these all these kind of
technical things in active inference
whereas when we're in flow or whether
when we're in skillful coping to use
dra's term we know we're not we're not
deploying attention onto that part of
the cognitive Machinery so it makes
perfect sense
why you know it's almost a contradiction
a you know to say that um yeah to say
that you could propositionally know who
you are whilst you're immersed in the
unfolding of reality that you're a part
of so I think I think active influence
actually gives a computational account
of of where that of where that kind of
Disconnect comes from but again I I I
think it's I think the important thing
to remember as well at least from an
active inference perspective is that
like one one is it really privileged
from the other um because again one's a
pragmatic mode and one's an epistemic
mode and you need both to minimize free
energy you need both to survive
fundamentally um and so although yes
that isolation that atomism is uh
painful in a way uh and you know you
could go all the way down to the
Buddhism and say that the craving the
dooka that comes from that self is the
kind of Heart of suffering
perhaps but at the same time uh I would
rather be a creature that can balance
epistemic and pragmatic needs than just
I I I just don't think it's feasible
given the type of things we are to be to
be solely
pragmatic cool well that's me that's my
sort of rant over um yeah no I I I agree
actually um yeah just sorry you jumped
in just no no go ahead I just yeah I
wanted to highlight um pretty much that
that I agree and I think again that's
kind kind of one of the interesting
things especially about um you know
heidig is account that kind of often
gets missed there's not this idea that
you know theoretical cognition is bad
science is bad quantification is bad or
that it's something that we could ever
actually put aside um so again it kind
of gets under
intellectualized a lot and you know
there's there's this tendency to kind of
overemphasize like you know like you
said kind of the importance of of uh
immersed practical coping but the idea
is but yeah we absolutely need both we
need all of these states um and when
things what happens when things go AR
right philosophically speaking is when
we forget that relationship and when we
kind of focus on one to the exclusion of
the other and forget how they
interrelate so yeah so it's I I
absolutely agree it's it's very much
this sense of of of yeah you you not
only can we not put these Tendencies
aside but we shouldn't want to we don't
have to to they're part they're
fundamentally part of what makes
cognition as complex as it is right yeah
yeah and again there's a kind of
self-perpetuating loop perhaps in which
when we're in this kind of more
epistemic mode we tend
towards um wanting that certainty okay
this is the way to be uh and I think
we've seen this in the kind of
westernization of something like a
mindfulness practice what if I could
just be mindful the whole you know
whatever that means and it's a very L
ter right depends one what mindfulness
practice you're doing but also like will
you being mindful to um how deep is that
metacognition there are loads of
questions that come up from that but my
point is that like because we're seeking
something to resolve our uncertainty and
it's an existential uncertainty about
how the world is again is a very decent
thought in my mind we're looking for
that kind of singular solution um
because that's the way that's the way we
resolve most of our uncertainty is just
to find out the fact but actually maybe
the the deeper truth is that this these
binary distinct like it's all it's all
Dynamic you don't want to have one over
the other and actually maybe that you
know there's plenty of cases where I'm
doing both pragmatic skillful coping and
some epistemic exploration right when I
open the door yes I'm not reifying the
door handle I'm not doing epistemic
foraging about the door handle but I
might be about well I'm gonna have a
dinner so occupy a very privileged
position where there's this complete
absorption and we have a kind of
technical um detailing about why that
might be the case I think the other
thing is that um I don't know whether
this is a strictly hiigaran idea I know
draus talks about it is that this kind
of dzign this being in the world brings
a bit a sense of
familiarity a uh you know draus would
talk about skillful coping um Hyer talks
about a-h handedness and as you say
we're kind of yes we are practical
creatures and the world is made for us
and we're made for the world and there
is this kind of mutual coupling so how
fundamental is the notion of familiarity
to
phenomenology and I guess a question
that comes up is are you know are we a
risk of losing that familiarity and and
if so
how yeah um brilliant question thanks
darus and I've I've actually been
thinking about this too from kind of a
different um direction of of of yeah
kind of looking at different discourses
that talk about the importance as active
inference does too of course if if
uncertainty and predictability and I
think there's there's very much this
need to again you know um as as we've
been saying before about practice and
Theory to resist binaries and then kind
of resist you know prioritizing one uh
over the other and so yeah on the one
hand absolutely as you said you know um
being the world involves in this this
sense of not only that you know the
world is made for us but more that you
know we we're enacting this world this
is this is our world that we're bringing
forth and so of course you know the
world that you never get is going to in
a sense reflect yourself back at you
it's your encountering it in terms of
you know your needs your capacities your
projects and so there is this this
intimate
familiarity with kind of practice as
such right with this idea of I mean that
kind of um there's a a point where
heiger talks about in sense like that
the weirdness if you really step back
and think about it of the fact that yeah
we're these creatures you just put us in
the world and doing stuff in order to
stay alive in order to striving for
goals that's just something that we can
naturally do that's just what it means
to be alive and so yeah so there is this
this kind of important sense of
familiarity but at the same time um
especially you know broadly in the
phenomenological tradition um and you
know kind of tangential theorist from
hunas to again all the book on there
there is this this emphasis on
uncertainty as well so yes this is our
world but we are fundamentally future
directed
creatures um we have to confront not
just confront but Embrace uncertainty at
every point and it's kind of that
fundamental many ways that we're running
away from a lot of the time but yeah
there's this sense that you know and we
we try to reduce our relationship to
uncertainty and unpredictability by just
cashing it out as planning anticipation
I can you know I can tame the week by
writing down exactly what's going to
happen but of course life doesn't work
like that so you know heiger talks about
confronting and and kind of being
directed to possibility as such um and
this importance of these moments
where the world isn't familiar anymore
right so he he talks about UNH um which
you know is is kind of it's it's it's
horror it's
eeriness um but it it it is quite
literally not at homeness right so where
that familiarity that we take for
granted is kind of the rug is pulled out
from under us and we need those moments
again not only to do philosophy but
actually to get a sense of the
existential import of what we're
confronting so there is this kind of
constant toity of familiarity yes we're
intimately familiar with practice as
practical beings but also with creatures
of uncertainty we're creatures of
unpredictability and that is kind of
what it means to be alive to confront
and and grapple with unpredictability
all the time well I'm so happy you
brought up the future as well there
because I think uh that's that's kind of
one of the big themes I do want to touch
upon before I do that um and so that was
kind of just a memo to
myself I think a lot of what you're
talking about here in terms of Highly go
maps onto his account of
mood um am I I think I might be speaking
speaking out of place it but I think H
puts a real emphasis on anxiety and
boredom almost like these are these kind
of two axes uh or or the end of the axis
of mood is that right and if so why
those two moods uh seems one quite
pessimistic um and two maybe not totally
faithful to our lived experience where
there's joy and relief and other
experiences yeah no that's a that's a
real question yeah that's um that's
exactly right so that's the the the kind
of part of his account his framework
that I'm looking at here right this this
idea of you know the the world matters
to us and it matters to us in a
particular way because we're attuned in
a particular way and yeah there are some
moods that kind of particularly
fundamental uh especially from the
perspective of somebody who wants wants
to make the everyday just strange enough
to be able to do philosophy about it and
so heiger does talk about you know other
effective states he does talk about joy
and love and anger and hate and all of
that sort of stuff but the existential
import of of anxiety and boredom I think
is is yeah the capacity to to kind of
again be like the broken Hammer right
cast the world into light by kind of by
disrupting how we navigate
kind of everyday sense making in
particularly radical ways right and so
especially with anxiety you know the the
key is that you're you're not afraid for
yourself as such you're kind of you're
experiencing this dread at the loss of
or at you know at the at your world at
your normal ways of sense making being
put into question um which reveals how
those uh operations of of sense making
actually function
um and so yeah so it's it seems like a
particularly PR account but um again
that's it's something you know that you
find in in in phenomenology I mean um
what was it I'm trying to remember the
three ones that SRA focused on in
particular so there were shame um as you
know a shame being kind of the proof of
the existence of other Minds right so we
could only feel shame if other Minds
actually stood because nothing could
make us feel shame the way that another
free
like human being another for itself
could and so it's it's that sense of you
know it's not deliberately it's not
saying this is all there is to The Human
Condition it's not saying these are the
only important effective States but it's
saying these are particularly
significant because of what they show us
about how the world and relational
cognition operate yes so they were
cheery weren't they um John Paul thank
you for that well yes you did say uh you
must act as if the whole world is
watching you which is slightly slightly
ominous um maybe true slightly ominous
though um great well yes let's jump to
Futurity uh my word of the week because
I've been reading your papers um you
quote Hyer who says that self-
projection upon for the sake of itself
again back to the hyphens is grounded in
the future and is an essential
characteristic of existentiality the
primary meaning of existentiality is the
future you then also say and I'll get it
up secondly I think that we can also
read the temporality of autopoetic
cognition in future weighted terms the
meaningful World generated by the
activity of the organism in
collaboration with its environment is
arguably defined by an orientation
towards Futurity in that the future
survivor of the system that provides the
framework for all its actions and the
salience that it produces in conjunction
with the situations it encounters so we
got kind of two strands there and a dual
Focus on the future one from haidinger
and one from the inactivist um tradition
obviously active inference is the future
and the unfolding the future is very
important in active but before we go
there um let's start with haiger why is
the future such a critical part of his
philosophy yeah uh great question darus
so haig's account uh of time in general
just to to kind of step back a bit um is
an account that fundamentally
fundamentally looks at live time in kind
of nonlinear terms right so the idea is
that um you can't kind of nicely neatly
separate past present and future into
these uh you know these these kind of
separable moments they're they always
intertwined and they have these feedback
loops in a sense where you know past and
future kind of shape each other in in
ways that we wouldn't expect if we had a
purely linear conception of time and and
just just to you know to to kind of to
add a little S note to that I think so
just from the little that I've read of
Act of inference that seems again a
particularly interesting point of
resonance right this idea of you know
past and future kind of revising each
other because what you're what you
experience what you're acting what
you're doing your predictions kind of
help you to revise your priz and there
this kind of yeah feedback loop of like
updating both predictions and and and
kind of Prior
beliefs just to jump in there before I
forget um I think a paper that actually
you would really enjoy but having
everyone would really enjoy is um yakob
how's got one called distrusting the
present where he basically takes the
phenomenology of um I think William
James called it the specious present and
I know H had a you know hle talked about
this kind of seeping of the past and the
future into the present and how this
yields a kind of flow of time and he
gives a theoretical account of that
under active inference terms in terms of
attention and precision waiting so just
little addendum there for anyone who's
interested um active inference has
dabbled into the phenomenology of time
and that's a really good place to start
but anyway back to back to
hiiga yeah cool no that's that's super
interesting I'll have to I'll have to
check out that
send we we're kind of we're operating
with this you know
nonlinear sense of of time where all of
these different aspects of of time can
revise each other so kind of moving away
from this you know focus on the now and
this this focus on need linear sequences
um and within that though so on the one
hand haiger argues for what he calls in
typically hiigaran terms the equ
primordiality of past present and future
which just means they're you know
equally primordial you you're not just
focused on the now each of these aspects
is kind of meant to be um yeah equally
significant equally fundamental in in
kind of structuring the way that we
experience things um but then there is
within all of that still this this kind
of emphasis on the future the stretching
into the future and um and you know so
how assess that explicitly a whole bit
but then of course the question is why
does he say that explicitly a whole bit
and so um part of the the reason for
that I argue is is
that the conception of ourselves or of
you know of the living organism I don't
think that this is just restricted to
the human the conception of the living
organism as a creature that has that
fundamentally wants to stay alive that's
concerned about itself that has projects
to fulfill whether that project is you
know going from here to there or you
know I want to become a bestselling
writer or whatever someone's existential
project might be the very idea of a
project is is always future directed so
if we're defined the very idea of
self-concern the very idea of
persistence uh self-maintenance
survival is always kind of going to be
fundamentally future it doesn't make
sense except in futural terms and the
reason that we need to try and survive
the reason that persistence is an effort
the reason that Annihilation is a
Potential Threat is because of
uncertainty right if there were no
openness uh if there were no sense of uh
something that could happen uh that you
need to adjust your responsiveness to
then there would you know then there
would just be stagnation there would be
nothing
um and and so and again going back to
that concept of adaptivity that we've
touched on a few times um and this is
why I think this is particularly
resonant there there are particular
resonances between hiigaran
phenomenology and an activism this very
idea of being able to respond to uh what
happens and of course for hiig all of
that is caught up in the overarching
importance of our limitations our
precariousness our finitude our
mortality right where
we be because there is this ultimate end
point to our future and everything
before that is open-ended that's kind of
the the reason the ultimate kind of
structural orientation that shapes
everything else that falls into place
around it so yeah you've you've got like
I said on the one hand this nonlinear
account of time but everything about it
privileges the future because it's the
future in a sense kind of explains
cognition explains life you couldn't be
the kind of creature that we are you
couldn't be a living creature without
this kind of future directedness and and
having to Grapple with uncertainty great
um and I guess before we make that
convergent point with AO pris activism
which which should be becoming clearer
for the
audience I think what's really uh
special about this account that H H
gives us is and I think it's your term
which I completely love is an ongoing
Futurity I said that to my master
supervisor um because I have only done
my master sorry you know haven't done my
PhD yet um so yes still very much a
layment to all of these but I said it to
my master supervisor because he's uh
he's loves Hy and actually did his
doctoral thesis on skillful coping um
and situated cognition so this is this
would really be up his street I said I I
absolutely love this I think this is an
amazing idea because yes you're right I
mean we think
of maybe again it's this cognitive bias
the past the present the future as these
kind of uh I don't know these kind of
rarified extensions and and the future
kind of going on ad infinitum but haig's
got this different perspective of an
ongoing Futurity and I think if I read
your work correctly it points to um it
points to this
notion that everything we have to do has
to be grounded in some sense because
we're we're fundamentally self-concerned
and to be self-c concerned is to um take
into account the future of yourself
right there's no self there's no self-c
concern without a reference point for
what you're going to be at time n plus
one so maybe it would be really uh
useful because I probably butchered that
to just give a little bit more about
what this concept is of kind of an
ongoing
Futurity awesome thank you and you
didn't butcher that at all that was
actually really incredibly well
articulated
no that was awesome thank you so I I
don't have much to to add on on top of
what you've said but yeah just to to
kind of essentially to to highlight what
you've mentioned exactly as you said the
very idea of of
self-concern means that there's always
going to be this this future
directedness you know there's like the
all of these Concepts that we talk about
in you know embodied cognition and
activism active inference to the you
know all of them early Mak sense in
terms of a relationship between n and n
plus one right or T and t+ one the
current state of the system and the next
state of the system is that a desirable
relation uh is it an undesirable
relation what does the system do to get
from this state to that state what
happens when that goes wrong motivation
normativity agency action all of those
only make sense in in in those terms
they're all about relations between the
current and futural states of of the
organism
um and exactly as I said for for haiger
the future and self-c concern are
fundamentally Linked In These ways and
there is very much this emphasis that
this
is this is a a Futurity that stretches
out until it doesn't right so it's never
a future that arrives and and I think
that especially that's something that
appeals to me about an activism this
idea that stagnation is death right that
there is the system's not going to stop
changing
um it can't the system is always going
to be a responding to stimuli it's
always going to be grappling with
uncertainty um and I guess that's also
something that happens in active
inference you're always you know the
brain doesn't suddenly go okay I've I've
predicted it I've done it I'm done box
is ticked I'm going to sit here now and
that's it um that only happens in that
only happens when the system ends yeah
um that yeah it's it's always
it's always this this kind of this year
this this stretched out Futurity and
even when you accomplish a particular
goal that you know that still is kind of
organized in this
broader framework of future directedness
of goal directedness where there's
always this overarching goal of of
self-c conern that's not something you
can achieve that's not something you can
be done with right you're only done with
it when it ends yeah yeah yeah exactly
that's wonderfully uh well said yeah our
being morbid it does sound nice to just
have a bit of stasis though but
unfortunately no unfortunately we're
just open and we're going to keep being
openly Dynamic um I think just to you
know cap off what we've been talking
about here in terms of this ongoing
Futurity if I may um I'd like to read
the sort of extension of that b you know
I talked about autop paresis being in
couched in future rated terms you say um
the survival of the organism is not
merely a simple not yet that is to be
anticipated or drawn out in a concrete
plan however this is a future that will
never arrive or be finally accomplished
it is an ongoing Futurity that orients
everything else and that can never be
closed off for the striving towards it
can only end not with being grasped or
secured for these are not possible but
with the annihilation of the framework
they have rendered meaningful with the
disintegration of the system for the
autopoetic Adaptive system stasis is
death there is O there is no end point
only the ultimate ceasing of those
processes of resistance istance and
precariousness that Define the very the
organism's very life ah I love that
that's that's so good um oh thank you no
it's it's really beautiful what I will
say uh again I'm not making a criticism
but I think it's just interesting is
that you also say haig's account again
we'll go jump in you know without
viewing Hyder the activ kind of one
extension but jumping back to Hyer Hyer
account advis us to view the futureal
dimension as having a special
significance one that be can be cashed
out in terms of a radical indeterminacy
that transcends mere predictive or
anticipatory models of Futurity now I'm
sure everyone's ears are just going
mental because they heard the word
predictive and we will get very excited
when we hear predictive so yes I take
the philosophical and phenomenological
point that there is uh yes that being
itself has to contend with the
indeterminacy of the future and and that
irregularity that unpredictability
shapes itself concerned in the sense
that everything is is uh projected to
some
t+1 I kind of I I I sense that there
isn't actually a conflict here or
attention with active inference um
because I think we're probably talking
about two different things here one is
that we have the kind of uh very
mechanistic technical uh capability to
predict in some t uh deep temporal way
and then the other is actually what is
the
phenomenological experience
in terms of like how I live or my living
is uh Guided by some future orientated
self-organization is that would you say
that's a kind of sufficient way to to
resolve that not under playing of uh
prediction but let's just say like that
prediction itself is not sufficient for
a hiigaran account of uh
being yeah I I think that's a great way
of putting it so especially yeah that
that last Point as you said so that
prediction is not sufficient um so it is
it is worth noting that you know when um
when heidig for example uses words like
anticipation or prediction he's trying
to contrast different ways that we have
of of relating uncertainty right and so
um yeah where the the kind of the the
more flatter or more reductive ways of
relating to uncertainty or in a sense
about trying to tame
uncertainty um and so if if there's I
assume that you know that the way that
we'd be using prediction that
circumstance isn't the way that you know
prediction is cashed out in for example
predictive processing that it it's I'm
assuming that you know that is a much
kind of richer more complicated process
as well especially where things can go
wrong right so the the possibility for
yeah for for things to go arrive for
what happens to be other than predicted
for there to be risk there to be failure
that's particularly important and um
yeah for a relationship to again to what
it is that we're predicting that is you
know is is less about kind of plotting
out a straightforward path that rules
Out Future uncertainty and is kind of
more I don't want to use the word
surfing uncertainty because that
immediately sounds like the the title of
Andy clar's wonderful book um but yeah
that's that's not what I mean you know
embracing uncertainty yeah yeah without
rolling out future uncertainty and so I
guess yeah if there's room in prediction
as it's cashed out in in active
inference for more richer ways of
relating to the Future then yeah there's
not really a conflict here no exactly
yeah I I think the
hiigaran
um anxiety of prediction is probably
very cable within a broader mathematical
understanding of what prediction or
prediction error is in in active
influence I think it's just good to iron
that out um in case anyone uh stumbles
across that the final thing you know I
know it's getting late you're in
Australia I'm in London it's not getting
late here the sun's coming up um is much
more a kind of meta conversation about
philosophy of science um this is
actually really I you know really what
your doctoral thesis and later works
have been looking at which is what is
the possibility for um finding
convergence points or finding enriching
dialogue between
phenomenology and Natural Sciences and
one uh approach has been to say that the
Natural Sciences are explanatory and
phenomenology is
descriptive um I know that's not the
approach that you or other contemporary
phenomenologists adopt if uh given that
why why is that a problematic uh
Duality excellent I'm so glad that you
bring this up and so yes so that's uh
something I've been turning my attention
to more recently so I've got a a paper
specifically about
phenomenologically motivated views of of
explanation and so I think um ultimately
that distinction of of kind of
relegating phenomenology to whatever is
not explanatory ends up missing out on a
lot of interesting resources that both
the phenomenological tradition and
contemporary phenomenology have um in
it's it ends up kind of giving us this
reductive view of phenomenology where
you know phenomenology is often cashed
out as kind of just
describing what a particular experience
is like um and you know which uh and
something I point out in in this paper
is which is is dangerous not just
because that's not what phenomenology
does phenomenology is a lot more
rigorous and systematic it's about
looking at what's underneath those
experiences is what's not obvious The
Experience um but you know if if we
start talking about so Dan Harvey makes
this this great point that phenomenology
is not just about the phenomen
phenomenal and if we just start
restricting phenomenology to describing
the phenomenal we might make all sorts
of commitments to what that phenomenal
is we might you know think phenomenology
is just about qualia um a concept that
I'm always very wary of um and and not
as interested in as as as um uh as maybe
I'm I'm expected to be um but also
generally I think there are models and
instances of phenomenological
explanations that are genuinely useful
and
insightful um about the mechanisms that
explain why phenomena are the way that
they are and I think that's especially
the case if we kind of complicate how we
think of explanations and that's where
where um I argue that phenomenology and
and an activism again kind of converge
right and and I assume again that that
active inference has you know lots of
useful things to say here too because
it's about looking away from that very
linear asymmetrical model of explanation
of here is the cause here is the effect
they're kind of you know a nice neat
sequence in time they're linear they're
cut off from each other right it's what
all of these discourses about cognition
show us whether it's in activism whether
it's activ inference is as we've already
talked about there's a lot more complex
feedback between past and present and
future there's a lot more feedback
between cause and effect um and so yeah
we need models of explanation that are
able to trace out those interesting
feedback loops and so I think
phenomenology especially has a lot to to
offer in in kind of that regard yeah I
guess um someone listening might be
curious about if there's a kind of
example in the
literature where phenomenology has been
able to give a explanatory account of a
phenomenon that might otherwise be sort
of only in the purview of the Natural
Sciences just wondering if if if that
you know if if you can think of one off
the top of your
head yeah so in uh in in that paper that
I mentioned I look at various accounts
psychological
explanation um they also look at a
couple of of recent attempts to um
conceptualize Evolution or kind of to
take up an inactive uh concept of of
evolution and to look at things like
minimal and basal cognition um but
perhaps for a kind of more accessible
example I think just going back to the
history of the development of embodied
cognition is is always is always useful
and this is kind of you know something
that comes up whenever or that I TR to
to throw in whenever people talk about
the dialogue between phenomenology and
cognitive science or the Natural
Sciences in general what could
phenomenology actually offer um what
could it bring that might be missed
otherwise and I mean the you know
embodied cognition developed the way
that it did
because um people read phenomenology and
you know because
Dyers and you know the the the mid 20th
century thought hey look this this's
stuff that these problems we're running
into when we're trying to develop you
know the most kind of primitive forms of
of of artificial systems um they're
actually problems that I kind of
predicted and and addressed and and set
out in all of these different
phenomenological Traditions from from
hidinger to to mer Pon and you know of
course um I mean for for driers that
kind of pointed to an almost
irresolvable problem um but yeah the you
know embodied cognition has taken the
shape that it has as a kind of huge set
of different discourses because these
these models of the relation between
cognizer and body and world as they were
cashed out and phenomenology proved
useful so that I think that in itself is
kind of a a useful like metadiscursive
example yeah yeah I mean draus when do
what computers can't do yet as like the
early
70s yeah that's right I love so it's
still still my my my favorite
sequel um idea for a SQL title right so
what computers can't do followed by what
computers still can't do yeah what
computers still can't do I mean yeah
it's fascinating again it's a
complete you know it could be another
hour and a half just on that um but
you're right I mean the the as far as I
can tell the AI folk are struggling um
with Just llms For Stuff where you
might want a little bit more embodiment
and you can um you know we can point
people to a company like versus who for
example are applying active inference uh
the active inference framework to
artificial intelligence and hopefully
there are going to be some you know I'm
sure exciting developments already
happening but I think the future is
bright um for the role of embodied
cognition in developing um intelligent
agents intelligent
artifacts Mar this was uh this was super
I mean for me like it's an opportunity
to discuss haiger with a hiigaran is
wonderful again I uh I'm a complete
Layman um I give a lot of credit to my
master supervisor again I only you know
only finished my Masters this year but
actually um you know I can imagine
having just left University to have an
educator like you would be a complete
privilege so thank you so much I
actually learned a wonderful
amount um and I mean actually before you
go maybe let people know you I said you
you're lectur philosophy one onong will
you focusing on the moment what can
people keep their eyes out for in terms
of your
output awesome thank you so much so
first thing I wanted to thank you for
having me on this has been absolutely
fantastic it's been such a fun
conversation and you're so brilliant to
talk to than I think it's so cool that
you're doing this at this stage in in
your career I thought you were you know
a post talk or something so you
certainly don't come across as a Layman
and this is like a really cool
initiative um and so yeah so in terms of
what people can keep an eye out for um
so I do have a book on heiger in time
coming out co-written with my wonderful
friend Emily Hughes uh it's coming at
April next year through rout lch so hiig
is alternative history of time I should
plug um and yeah and other than that I'm
working on a whole bunch of projects
actually looking at synesthesia and
counteracts among other things so yeah
nice all right well that that book is
extremely exciting and thank you so much
for your kind words yeah I mean um all
credit goes to the The Institute um for
letting me do this yeah I mean to be
honest uh you know I've never actually
announced who I am we sort of just
kicked off this series with Carl as me
being complete random yeah I mean I yeah
as I said earlier I mean I finished my
masters in September but discovered
active inflence about a year ago and has
have just absolutely fall in love with
it and just its capacity to bring into
the picture insights from phenomenology
philosophy physics maths which I think
is exactly the interdisciplinary
approach that people have been talking
about but haven't been fulfilling their
promise on um but thank you that's
that's really very kind of you and and
yeah I mean hopefully uh we're going to
keep getting wonderful guests Like You
on to to educate me and our audience
even more uh Marilyn thank you so much
once again thank you so much darus it's
been awesome cool thank you guys thank
you